Just like we did with NumPy arrays,
就像处理 NumPy 数组一样
we can perform element-wise arithmetic operations on Pandas series.
我们可以对 Pandas 序列的元素进行算术运算
In this video, we will look at
本视频将讲解
arithmetic operations between Pandas series and single numbers.
Pandas 序列与单个数字之间的算术运算
Let's create a new series that holds a grocery list of fruits.
我们先新建一个记录水果杂货的序列
The first argument we pass in is the data,
这里输入的第一个参数是数据
and the second argument is the index labels.
第二个参数是索引标签
We can modify the data in fruits by performing basic arithmetic operations.
我们可以用基本算术运算修改序列 fruits 的数据
We can add two to each element in fruits,
比如给 fruits 的各元素加 2
subtract two, multiply by two, and divide by two.
让各元素减 2、乘以 2 或除以 2
We can also apply mathematical functions from
我们还可以用 NumPy 的数学函数
NumPy such as square root to all the elements of a series.
比如 sqrt 求序列各元素的平方根
Let's import NumPy and take a look at our fruit series again.
导入 NumPy 再次查看序列 fruits
Using NumPy, we can get the square root of each element like this.
像这样 我们就能用 NumPy 求出各元素的平方根
And the exponential of each element,
或各元素指数函数的值
and each element to the power of two.
或各元素的平方了
Pandas also allows us to apply arithmetic operations on selected items in a series.
Pandas 还能对序列某个特定项进行算术运算
Here's the fruit series again.
还是这个序列 fruits
We can add two to just the banana's item, like this.
我们可以像这样只给 bananas 一项加 2
And let's subtract two from apples using its numerical index.
也可以用数字索引 让 apples 一项减 2
We can double the apples and oranges like this,
还可以像这样让 apples 和 oranges 乘以 2
and divide apples and oranges by two like this.
或像这样让 apples 和 oranges 除以 2
You can also apply arithmetic operations on a Pandas series of
你还可以对具备多种数据类型的 Pandas 序列应用算术运算
mixed data types provided that
前提是
the arithmetic operation is defined for all data types in the series.
算术运算的定义适用于序列里的所有数据类型
To demonstrate this, let's go back to our grocery's list from the previous video,
以上个视频提到的杂货表为例
and let's multiply this series by two,
让该序列乘以 2
since the multiplication operation is defined for both strings and numbers.
因为乘法运算的定义同时适用于字符串和数字
This code doesn't return an error.
所以代码没有返回出错提示
Multiplying a string by two simply repeats it.
字符串相乘也就是重复同一个字符串两次
If you were to apply an operation that was valid for numbers but not strings,
如果你要进行的运算只适用于数字 但不适用于字符串
for instance division, you would get an error.
比如除法 代码就会提示出错
So, when you have mixed data types in your Pandas series,
所以 当 Pandas 序列具有多种数据类型时
make sure the arithmetic operations you
请确保你要进行的算术运算
use are defined for all the data types in your series.
定义适用于序列里的所有数据类型